Guide to the Betty Zane Grosso Collection of Zane and Dolly Grey Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Betty Zane Grosso collection of Zane and Dolly Grey papers
1900-1985
WA MSS S-2705
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8
(17 boxes)
The collection documents the life and work of the American writer Zane Grey and his wife Dolly Grey, and to some extent the lives of their children. The papers chiefly consist of correspondence between Zane and Dolly Grey from the time they met until his death, circa 1900-1939. Their letters document Zane Grey's frequent travels throughout the American West and in the South Pacific, his career as a writer, their marriage, and the growth of their family. The collection also includes some correspondence with others; a draft of Zane Grey's autobiography; Dolly Grey's diaries; photographs and ephemera; and ten films. Many of the films apparently document hunting and fishing expeditions, but the collection also includes a print of the 1936 Australian film "White Death," in which Grey was featured as himself, and two documentaries about Zane Grey produced in 1985 by his family.
Grosso, Betty Zane Grey
Grey, Zane, 1872-1939
Grey, Lina Elise, -1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Serendipity Books on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2002-2003; Gift of Gary and Bridget McMahon, 2003; purchased from William Reese Company, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 10-17 (motion picture film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 8 (VHS cassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Zane and Dolly Grey
Zane Grey, writer of popular adventure stories about the American West, was born Pearl Zane Gray in Zanesville, Ohio, in 1872, to Lewis M. Gray, a dentist, and Josephine Zane Gray. Changing his name to Zane Grey in early adulthood, he studied dentistry at the University of Pennsylvania, graduating in 1896, and started his own practice in New York City. In November 1905 he married Lina Elise Roth, known as Dolly, a graduate of Hunter College. The couple settled in Lackawaxen, Pennsylvania, where they began a family that grew to include three children: Romer (1909-1976), Betty (1912-2007), and Loren (1915-2007). Dolly Grey strongly supported her husband's ambitions to make his living as a writer, helping to edit his work and manage his career as he became increasingly successful. Despite his long absences from home and several acknowledged extramarital affairs, their marriage remained strong and Dolly Grey continued to champion Zane Grey's work following his death of heart failure in 1939.
Zane Grey's prolific output included best-selling novels such as Riders of the Purple Sage, The Lone Star Ranger, and Under the Tonto Rim, many of which were made into equally successful Hollywood films. Grey lived the adventurous life he wrote about, spending months of each year camping in the Arizona desert or fishing off Tahiti and Australia. He was as famous for fishing as he was for writing about it, holding a number of world records including a 1,036-pound tiger shark.
Dolly Grey died in 1957 at the age of 74 in Altadena, California, where the family had moved circa 1920. She was buried beside her husband in Lackawaxen, Pennsylvania. After her death the Grey children continued stewardship of their father's legacy through management of Zane Grey, Inc., formed in 1933 to manage Grey's assets and the rights to his work. In 1931 Betty Zane Grey married Robert W. Carney, with whom she had two daughters; she married George D. Grosso in 1951.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the life and work of the American writer Zane Grey and his wife Dolly Grey, and to some extent the lives of their children. The papers chiefly consist of correspondence between Zane and Dolly Grey from the time they met until his death, circa 1900-1939. Their letters document Zane Grey's frequent travels throughout the American West and in the South Pacific, his career as a writer, their marriage, and the growth of their family. The collection also includes some correspondence with others; a draft of Zane Grey's autobiography; Dolly Grey's diaries; photographs and ephemera; and ten films. Many of the films apparently document hunting and fishing expeditions, but the collection also includes a print of the 1936 Australian film "White Death," in which Grey was featured as himself, and two documentaries about Zane Grey produced in 1985 by his family.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1900-1969. II. Writings, 1906-1938. III. Dolly Grey Diaries, 1906-1954. IV. Other Papers, 1905-1950. V. Audiovisual Materials, 1935-1985.
Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Western stories; Photographic prints; Motion pictures (visual works); Videocassettes; Authors; Grey, Lina Elise, -1957; Grey, Loren, 1915-2007; Grey, Romer, 1909-1976; Grey, Zane, 1872-1939; Grosso, Betty Zane Grey
- Correspondence, 1900-1969; Series I; 5; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Zane Grey to Dolly Grey, Dolly Grey to Zane Grey, and Other Correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  The series consists chiefly of correspondence between Zane and Dolly Grey. It also includes letters to Zane and Dolly Grey from family, friends, publishers, and fans. A small amount of correspondence to Betty Zane Grosso is also present.
  Dolly Grey's letters to her husband often enclose correspondence from third parties to Zane Grey, bearing her own annotations, as well as snapshots of their children.
  - Zane Grey to Dolly Grey
    - 1900-1901, 2 (Box 1)
    - Undated early letters, circa 1901 (Box 1)
    - 1902, 5 (Box 1)
    - 1903 (Box 1)
    - 1904, 2 (Box 1)
    - 1905, 2 (Box 1)
    - 1906, 2 (Box 1)
    - 1907-1908, 2 (Box 1)
    - 1911-1915, 2 (Box 1)
    - 1916, 2 (Box 1)
    - 1917, 7 (Box 1)
    - 1918, 6 (Box 1)
    - 1920, 2 (Box 1)
    - 1921, 3 (Box 1)
    - 1922, 11 (Box 1)
    - 1922, 8 (Box 2)
    - 1923, 8 (Box 2)
    - 1924, 12 (Box 2)
    - 1925, 5 (Box 2)
    - 1926, 8 (Box 2)
    - 1927, 4 (Box 3)
    - 1928, 8 (Box 3)
    - 1929, 4 (Box 3)
    - 1930, 3 (Box 3)
    - 1931, 4 (Box 3)
    - 1933, 2 (Box 3)
    - 1928-1936, 10 (Box 3)
    - Undated, 3 (Box 3)
    - Telegrams, 1920-1928; 12 (Box 3)
  - Dolly Grey to Zane Grey
    - 1900 (Box 4)
    - 1901, 2 (Box 4)
    - 1902 (Box 4)
    - 1903 (Box 4)
    - 1904, 2 (Box 4)
    - 1905, 2 (Box 4)
    - 1913, 2 (Box 4)
    - 1914, 2 (Box 4)
    - 1915 (Box 4)
    - 1916, 2 (Box 4)
    - 1917 (Box 4)
    - 1918, 2 (Box 4)
    - 1919 (Box 4)
    - 1920, 3 (Box 4)
    - 1921, 3 (Box 4)
    - 1922, 2 (Box 4)
    - 1923, 2 (Box 4)
    - 1924, 3 (Box 4)
    - 1925, 2 (Box 4)
    - 1926 (Box 4)
    - 1927 (Box 4)
    - 1928 (Box 4)
    - 1929-1931 (Box 4)
    - 1932 (Box 4)
    - 1933, 3 (Box 4)
    - 1934-1935 (Box 4)
    - 1936, 3 (Box 5)
    - Undated, 4 (Box 5)
    - Empty envelopes, 1901-1936; 2 (Box 5)
  - Other Correspondence
    - Associated Sunday Magazine, 1914 (Box 5)
    - Bailey, Mary Hilliard, undated (Box 5)
    - Bowen, Ed, 1934 (Box 5)
    - Campbell, Berenice, 1931 (Box 5)
    - Carney, Robert, 1928-1933, undated; 4 (Box 5)
    - Cevallos y Lupio, 1925 (Box 5)
    - Cleveland, Elizabeth, 1934 (Box 5)
    - Country Gentleman, 1924 (Box 5)
    - Dawson, Betty, 1935 (Box 5)
    - Field and Stream, 1922-1928 (Box 5)
    - Grey family, undated (Box 5)
    - Grey, Ida, 1917-1933, undated (Box 5)
    - Grey, Loren, 1928 (Box 5)
    - Grey, R.C., 1901-1932, undated; 2 (Box 5)
    - Grey, Romer, 1914-1961; 2 (Box 5)
    - Grosset and Dunlap, 1923 (Box 5)
    - Grosso, Betty Zane, 1919-1955; 7 (Box 5)
    - Grosso, George, to Betty Zane Grosso, 1944 (Box 5)
    - Harper and Brothers, 1913-1928 (Box 5)
    - Hearst Newspapers, 1928 (Box 5)
    - James, Alvah, 1915 (Box 5)
    - Kerr, Christopher to Betty Zane Grosso, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Ladies' Home Journal, 1924-1926 (Box 5)
    - McGowan, John, 1924 (Box 5)
    - The Popular Magazine, 1914 (Box 5)
    - St. Louis Public Library, 1925 (Box 5)
    - Smith, Hildred, undated (Box 5)
    - Stratton-Porter, Gene, 1924 (Box 5)
    - Summers, J. L., 1926 (Box 5)
    - Ussher, Kathleen, 1925 (Box 5)
    - Witt, Diane Gray to Betty Zane Grosso, 1969 (Box 5)
    - YMCA Publishing House of Denmark, 1924 (Box 5)
    - "Emmeline", circa 1916 (Box 5)
    - "Katcha", 1932 (Box 5)
    - Other correspondents, 1901-1962 (Box 5)
    - Fan Mail, 1913-1932 (Box 5)
    - Fan Mail (Australia), 1936 (Box 5)
    - Empty envelopes (Box 5)
    - Blank stationery (Box 5)
- Writings, 1906-1938; Series II; 8
  Arranged chronologically.
  Series II contains writings of Zane Grey, including a typescript draft of his unfinished autobiography, a notebook in which he discusses writing style, and two untitled short pieces.
  - Notebook, 1906-1908 (Box 6)
  - "The Living Past: The Autobiography of Zane Grey", typescript carbon, 1938 November 10; 5 (Box 6)
  - "Out of the fog [...]," autograph manuscript, no year December 27 (Box 6)
  - "One of Dad's description of women," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 6)
- Dolly Grey Diaries, 1906-1954; Series III; 1; (1 box)
  This series contains Dolly Grey's diaries. The first volume documents the first year of her marriage, after which there is a large gap. The rest of the diaries chronicle her daily life from 1924 to 1939, and then with gaps from 1940 to 1954.
  - Diary, 1906 (Box 6)
  - Diaries, 1924-1938; 5 (Box 6)
  - Wall calendar, 1939 (Box 6)
  - Diaries, 1940-1954; 7 (Box 6)
    None present for 1942-1943, 1946, 1949-1951, 1953
- Other Papers, 1905-1950; Series IV; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arranged roughly by type of material.
  Series IV contains photographs of Zane Grey including formal portraits, images of him camping and fishing, and images of the Grey family, including some publicity photos taken some time after Zane Grey's death. The series also contains miscellaneous other papers such as clippings, notes, shopping lists, writings by Dolly Grey and Betty Zane Grosso, and a reflection about Zane Grey by a college classmate.
  - Photographs, 1920-1950; 7 (Box 7)
    Also stored in: Box 9 Oversize
  - Wedding announcement, 1905 (Box 7)
  - "Zane Grey the Man" by Wiborn, typescript carbon, corrected, 1924 (Box 7)
  - Postcards, bookmark with Zane Grey portrait, undated (Box 7)
  - Poems by Dolly Grey and Betty Zane Grosso, undated (Box 7)
  - Notes and shopping lists, 1925, undated; 4 (Box 7)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 7)
  - Printed ephemera, 1902, undated (Box 7)
  - Documents regarding claim against McClure's Magazaine, 1922 (Box 7)
  - Poster: "Sol Lesser presents Zane Grey (himself) in South Sea Adventures", 1932 (Box 18 (Broadside))
- Audiovisual Materials, 1935-1985, undated; Series V; (10 films)
  This series consists of eight reels of film including home movies of the Grey family, footage of Grey in Australia and New Zealand, and the commercial film "White Death." It also includes two documentary films in the VHS format apparently made by Gary McMahon, husband of Betty Zane Grosso's granddaughter Bridget Kerr McMahon.
  Boxes 10-17: Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 8: Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "White Death R.5", [1936]; 16mm film, 300 feet (Box 10 (cold storage))
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "Color / Dad / Tahiti / few feet", undated; 16mm film, 300 feet (Box 11 cold storage)
  - "16mm 1935-36 Australia Shots of the girls shell gathering / Shooting 'White Death' / 16mm Australia B&W cut outs", 1935-1936; Several 16mm film rolls, length unknown (Box 12 cold storage)
  - "Zane Grey / 35 mm [illegible word(s)] / NZ INC Sharks. / Maco (?) Shark / Fish [illegible word(s)] / Part 2 Eastman Neg Safety Film 16mm [etc: printed label]", undated; 35mm film, 700 feet (Box 13 cold storage)
  - "Color UTAH-WYO 1937 / ZG UMPQUA only color / Quest PRODS Zane Grey #2", 16mm film, 250 feet (Box 14 cold storage)
  - "RG [Romer Grey] ORE-COLO some [illegible, possibly "rivers"]", undated; 16mm film, 175 feet (Box 15 cold storage)
  - "Neg Loren & RG [Romer Grey] – UMPQUA 1953 / June 1953 / B&W Neg / LG & RG Umpqua Point", 16mm film, 375 feet (Box 16 cold storage)
  - Unidentified, undated; 16mm film, 175 feet (Box 17 cold storage)
  - "Zane Grey: An American Legend." Zane Grey / Collector's Series, 1985. A Gary McMahon Production, Copyright 1985. "…a fresh and revealing look into the life of America's premier storyteller.", WAMSSS2705_0001; 1; 00:29:14 (Box 8, Item barcode 39002102300242)
  - "Zane Grey's Outdoor Adventures" Zane Grey / Collector's Series, 1985. "Two complete rare travelogues of the legendary Zane Grey, with an introduction by Loren Grey.", WAMSSS2705_0002; 1; 00:59:55 (Box 8, Item barcode 39002102300259)
- Oversize Materials
  - Photographs (in Series IV), circa 1950; 2 (Box 9 Oversize)
  - "Zane Grey," broadsheet of profile of the author (in Series IV), undated (Box 9 Oversize)